<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-29T00:03:30-08:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nova Machina</title><subtitle>An exploration of agility, learning, and growth.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">An Amazon employee’s environmental manifesto</title><link href="/environment/2020/12/28/amazon-environment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Amazon employee’s environmental manifesto" /><published>2020-12-28T13:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-28T13:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/environment/2020/12/28/amazon-environment</id><content type="html" xml:base="/environment/2020/12/28/amazon-environment.html">&lt;p&gt;Could it be that Amazon is good for the environment? What about the cardboard boxes, and the trucks, and the power-hungry data centers? To understand what Amazon brings to the table, we need to look at the alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/amazon-robot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Amazon robot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, leave aside the observation that we all should consume less. This would be good for the environment, but it’s a different problem. Let’s just say that people are going to consume a certain amount per capita. We have two ways to make a smaller footprint on the planet while providing that stuff: fewer people, and greater efficiency.  Population seems to be taking care of itself, as people move to cities and have fewer children - a demographic transition. That leaves efficiency as the area where we can make real headway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;efficiency-is-good-for-the-environment&quot;&gt;Efficiency is good for the environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a great thought experiment from the 1990s: what if we increased our efficiency by a factor of four? Then we could double our standard of living while cutting our resource use in half. This was proposed by Amory and Hunter Lovins and Ernst von Weizsacker, in their book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Factor-Four-Doubling-Halving-Resource-ebook/dp/B00ID6S61S/ref=sr_1_7?keywords=factor+four+lovins&amp;amp;qid=1578527501&amp;amp;sr=8-7&quot;&gt;Factor of Four&lt;/a&gt;. Their focus was on the consumer – things like energy usage in the home, recycling, efficient cars. And certainly these things are very important. However, the resources used by businesses - to make and distribute things - are greater than what we use as consumers. For example, energy used in homes is only about one quarter of the energy used in all buildings (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eia.gov/energyexplained/us-energy-facts/&quot;&gt;US EIA report&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you make businesses more efficient? First, you cut waste, in the way that Toyota pioneered with their hyper-efficient car factories. This has been called lean manufacturing, and it’s based on an innovative way of organizing big companies, with intentionally small units. Amazon has extended this model of small teams and small batches of work to retail and online services and electronics. You might think that Toyota’s cost advantage comes from people working harder, or automation, but mainly it comes from a more efficient way of organizing people. James Womack and his coauthors describe this in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Machine-That-Changed-World-Revolutionizing/dp/0743299795/&quot;&gt;The Machine That Changed the World&lt;/a&gt;, with their analysis of the global auto industry of the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amazons-efficiency&quot;&gt;Amazon’s Efficiency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same can be said of Amazon. It’s a more dynamic organization than most, with employees that are empowered to solve problems as they uncover them, and have the means to solve them because the teams are are so small and modular. This way of organizing people leads to savings and efficiencies in countless small ways, which add up to a more efficient system. The efficient system needs less fuel, less electricity, less real estate, and creates less pollution… than the alternative. Keep in mind that the alternative is a system of traditional warehouses and transportation, which Amazon out-competes because the traditional system is so wasteful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tight-coordination&quot;&gt;Tight coordination&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, you use information systems to coordinate things. How does Amazon offer two-day delivery? By making smart use of information systems. Lots of computing power, and tight coordination. The part that the customer sees is fast delivery. Behind the scenes, all sorts of things are being tracked and optimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shared-infrastructure&quot;&gt;Shared infrastructure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you provide shared infrastructure to businesses and consumers across the economy. The cloud computing offered by Amazon Web Services uses less energy than the scattered data centers once owned by individual businesses. There’s efficiency from scale, for example with cooling systems, and more opportunity to share hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, shoppers save countless trips to the store to buy things, if they have a delivery truck make the rounds instead. (This doesn’t improve the picture in Manhattan, where delivery trucks replace some very efficient foot traffic rather than SUVs, but it’s a benefit in most places.) The delivery truck consumes gas, but it saves many separate trips by gas-guzzling cars and in the end uses less gas. Less global warming, less air pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;renewable-energy&quot;&gt;Renewable energy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The icing on the cake is when Amazon commits to 100% renewable energy, and meeting the Paris Agreement 10 years early. You could say that the bigger contribution is still Amazon’s efficiency, because the rest of the economy is compelled to be more efficient in order to compete with Amazon. But it’s still a big deal when the shoppers’ SUVs are replaced with electric-powered delivery trucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-real-impact-on-the-environment&quot;&gt;A real impact on the environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how do I feel about working at Amazon, as a former environmental consultant and concerned citizen? I feel like I’m part of the solution. In fact, I feel like this is the best contribution I can possibly make to helping the environment, to work on root causes rather than just patching things up. After looking for ways to move the dial for over 40 years, this is it - make the economy more efficient. Government regulations come and go, educating people is a slow process. If you want to make substantial change, tie it to economic incentives and influence the way the whole economy operates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another post we’ll look at a painful consequence of the more efficient economy - the loss of jobs. But let’s keep in mind that those jobs needed to go away, as part of the efficiency that will let us continue to live on this planet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="environment" /><summary type="html">Could it be that Amazon is good for the environment? What about the cardboard boxes, and the trucks, and the power-hungry data centers? To understand what Amazon brings to the table, we need to look at the alternatives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The story of Stack Overflow’s amazing relevance</title><link href="/relevance/2020/12/18/stack-overflow-relevance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The story of Stack Overflow’s amazing relevance" /><published>2020-12-18T13:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-18T13:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/relevance/2020/12/18/stack-overflow-relevance</id><content type="html" xml:base="/relevance/2020/12/18/stack-overflow-relevance.html">&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, a large software company in Redmond wanted to publish the best pages on the web for developers. But they ran into competition from an unexpected source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/stack-overflow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stack Overflow wins&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-discovery&quot;&gt;A discovery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back when data flowed from Google like lemonade from Rock Candy Mountain (before 2012), this large company was able to track the performance of it’s pages for specific terms that the pages were about. A team of us were also able to track the performance of competitors’ pages for the same terms. What we found was surprising: the top performer for the majority of terms was &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/&quot;&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;. The second most popular site was Wikipedia, and the company’s own pages usually didn’t rank on the first page of search results at all. This meant that when people searched for terms on Google that were related to the company’s pages, the top search results were dominated by Stack Overflow. This pattern held true across hundreds of search terms and tens of thousands of pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because the developer community on the web had created more links to Stack Overflow than to the company’s pages. This had to mean they liked Stack Overflow better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-was-this-surprising&quot;&gt;Why was this surprising?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stack Overflow’s popularity for these topics was surprising because the company’s own pages were written by professional technical writers, and then professionally edited. Stack Overflow’s posts were written by volunteer developers using broken English. Many of the Stack Overflow posts were barely intelligible - just readable enough to convey their technical idea, nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-made-stack-overflow-so-much-better&quot;&gt;What made Stack Overflow so much better?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stack Overflow did a number of things right. At least, these are the things that set them apart, and in hindsight probably were worked very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;minimalism-worked&quot;&gt;Minimalism worked&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting feature of the Stack Overflow posts was that they were extremely short. In some cases, they were just a couple of sentences with a code snippet. Since each post was treated as a web page, this made Google searches very effective for finding relevant content. It also meant that visitors didn’t need to spend lots of time reading. In some cases, the pages created by the company had thousands of words - they might run to more than 10 pages if printed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;relevance-was-the-key&quot;&gt;Relevance was the key&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that the minimalism of Stack Overflow got more quickly to the point than the wordy, polished style of the company’s site. Excess text didn’t get in the way of relevance - useful topics were covered accurately, and nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the usefulness of the pages also came from the way the question-and-answer approach structured the information around tasks and problems. This is usually what we want when we Google something - to solve a problem or task. We don’t want to know about all of the features of some product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the relevance of the questions and answers was made clear by the voting system, a kind of gamification. More than a way to rate individual answers, this was also a way to build trust in the site and tap into the energy of the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;community-effort-made-it-happen&quot;&gt;Community effort made it happen&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly more important than the details of how the content was formed - its conciseness, relevance, accuracy - was the mechanism that made it all possible. This was the community of software developers who wrote the questions and answers. They acted out of a mix of enlightened self-interest and social ties. They knew what worked for them, and made it happen through open discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-it-went-from-there&quot;&gt;Where it went from there&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did we do about this at the large company? To be honest, not much. At least, not quickly. If you go back today to the large company’s site, the style has evolved a bit, to be more concise. This is good. But even now, eight years later, the pages are organized around product features rather than common problems or tasks. There’s no voting system for the main documentation. There’s a Q&amp;amp;A area similar to Stack Overflow, but somehow it’s not very active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to hear from users why the Q&amp;amp;A feature hasn’t caught on - is it too similar to Stack Overflow? Too new? (It appears to have been released just this year.) I’m no longer with the company so I don’t know the background behind that. If in fact it’s just a problem of being new, it’ll be interesting to see where the Q&amp;amp;A section goes in the next couple of years - perhaps it’ll eclipse the main documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amazon-vs-stack-overflow&quot;&gt;Amazon vs Stack Overflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we can take away from Stack Overflow is that relevance is the single most important thing about what we write. It’s much more important than style and polish. A technical user is going to ask “Does this page solve my problem?”, nothing more. Forget your assumptions from print publishing about the need for writing to be spotless. Forget about impressing people with how educated you are. Just convey an idea in the quickest way possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lean--minimalist&quot;&gt;Lean = minimalist&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found that this idea of minimalist writing resonates very well at Amazon. The Amazon culture is conditioned by lean ideas inherited from Toyota, where anything that doesn’t ultimately provide value to the customer should be considered waste and rooted out. This includes writing that doesn’t solve a specific problem. Lengthy documents and pages are frowned upon. There’s often no documentation at all, especially if there are other ways of sharing information, like through an automated tool or a web service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This minimalism can feel a bit scary sometimes, even chaotic - so little is written down. But it’s by design. A technical writer at Amazon often spends more time cutting content (written by engineers) than adding new. And this is a good thing, as the web community has shown with its embrace of Stack Overflow. By erring on the side of not documenting things, Amazon can document only that which is essential - and ensure relevance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;open--community-effort&quot;&gt;Open = community effort&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major internal platforms at Amazon are as open as Stack Overflow to collaboration. Everyone shares an enormous wiki with millions of pages, and nearly all of those pages can be commented and edited by anyone in the company who sees a need for a correction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon also has an internal question and answer platform that  works much like Stack Overflow. It has the openness of the wiki, and includes the same sort of gamification and focus on problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Amazon has fully embraced the Stack Overflow model - relevance made possible by being open to the broadest possible community of contributors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="relevance" /><summary type="html">Once upon a time, a large software company in Redmond wanted to publish the best pages on the web for developers. But they ran into competition from an unexpected source.</summary></entry></feed>